Guide to the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- THE WRITING OF THEIR BOOKS, ETC., 1832-1840; C.
  - Marie, ou l'Esclavage aux Etats-Unis, 9 (Box 30)
    We now find that Marie was apparently the very first novel ever to be published in the United States making the tragedy of the colored races, especially of the Mulatto or free Negros, its central theme. The first comparable book in this country was an anonymous work, later claimed by the historian Hildreth, which was got out in 1836, the year after Marie. The classic, Uncle Tom's Cabin, by Harriet Beecher Stowe, did not appear until 1852. We have here therefore an Uncle Tom's Cabin written 17 years too soon and never until 1959 translated into English. (Cf. Introduction by Alvis Tinnin in that translation, Stanford University Press)
    From a number of other points of view this book has genuine significance. Among the questions that it raises are the following:
    1. Where did Beaumont get his idea and his attitude? I think it will be very interesting to explore the background of Beaumont's thinking in Chateaubriand, in the uprising of Toussaint L'Ouverture, and in such earlier Romantic classics as Paul et Virginie. It will be possible, I think, to show that the tragic black or mulatto first appears as an incidental character, on the margins of the story as the servant of the master, etc., and then from the wings slowly comes to center stage.
    2. Where did Beaumont get the actual material for his own story? Here we already have in the Tocqueville collection and in my book extensive materials to explain the factual content, and the moving incidents which helped to give body and emotional content to the novel. Here are the story of the crazed Negro and the almshouse, the French exile of Lake Oneida, the Journey into the wilderness of Michigan, etc., etc., all from Beaumont's personal experience in America. (see Chapter 38 of my book.) As a further aid we have in the Tocqueville collection a microfilm of an M.A. Thesis written on Beaumont's Marie some years ago by a Kentucky student, who made us this present in return for the privilege of using the Tocqueville materials. (see D.V.)
    3. The relation of Marie to French politics and Beaumont's career. In the 1830's a number of French writers appear to have attacked the slavery problem in less literary ways, and Beaumont later went on to become the champion of emancipation for the North Africans in the French colonies. In the Chamber, railroads and colonies were his specialties. In French life the emancipation question had a distinct place.
    A number of the above suggestions were explored by Alvis L. Tinnin in his Ph.D. Thesis for the French Department (which see). See also Tinnin's Introduction to the Barbara Chapman translation of Marie (Stanford University Press) and Fabian's Review (D.IV.o.).
    GWP (1955, 1964)
  - Marie, ou l'Esclavage aux Etats-Unis (Box 31)
  - L'Irlande, 10
    Nine bundles and some miscellany. Seen by GWP at Beaumont-la-Chartre in 1930. Acquired in 1956 from Mme de Larminat. These consist of a great miscellaneous mixture of notes, statistics, ideas, topics, and quotes from other authorities. They contain at the same time drafts (ca. 1839) of a considerable section of Beaumont's book L'Irlande, and at least some materials, I should judge, on a greater part of the chapters. The titles or labels put on each package by GWP in 1930 correspond only roughly to the contents, but, in comparison with the printed book, one might be able to set these papers in order and shed some light on the composition of the work. There are materials also on the revision of the sixth printed translation of the book, edited by W.C. Taylor, 2 volumes, 1839, with marginal notes; and a copy of the first edition in 2 volumes with Gustave de Beaumont's autograph and a few pencilled marginalia, also acquired from Mme de Larminat. GWP owns a French edition or two.
    Description of contents, prepared by Eduardo Nolla, August 1985:
    Box 1
    Manuscript of vol. I of L'Irlande.
    Box 2
    Beaumont's copy of 1839 English edition, with marginalia.
    Manuscript of vol II of L'Irlande.
    Box 3
    Book catalogues and lists of books.
    Outline of L'Irlande.
    Program of 11 June 1840 session of the Academie Francaise. Prize of 6,000
    Francs for L'Irlande.
    Lecture pour l'Academie.
    Notes for Vol. II.
    Boxes 4-6
    Notes and drafts for vol. I of L'Irlande.
    Also:
    -Marginalia, probably by Tocqueville, in several chapters.
    -Note by Drummond to Gustave de Beaumont
    -Visiting card of Comtesse de Meulan.
    -Note by Penhonet [?].
    -5 issues of the Dublin Evening Post (January 12, 1837; February 7, 1837; February 9, 1837; March 25, 1837). -1 issue of the Journal des Debats (22 mai 1825).
    Boxes 6-8
    -Rodd to Gustave de Beaumont, London, July 3, 1837.
    -George C. Lewis to Gustave de Beaumont, 17 Henrietta Street, Cavendish
    Sq., July 20, 1835. -George C. Lewis to Gustave de Beaumont, 17 Henrietta Street, Cavendish
    Sq., no date. -Notes by George C. Lewis.
    -Visiting cards of William Wood and George Combe (of 23 Charlotte Square).
    -A Bill entitled: An Act for the regulation of the Proceedings and Practice in certain Offices, and the Salaries and Fees of certain Officers of the High Court of Chancery in England.
    -Charles Renouard, "Memoire sur la statistique de la justice civile en France." (Extrait de la Revue de Legislation et de Jurisprudence, tome I, 5e livraison). Paris: Au Bureau de Redaction, Feevrier 1835)
    -2 issues of the Journal des Debats (2 septembre 1835; 17 mai 1838).
    -1 issue of The Freeman's Journal (August 18, 1838).
    -4 issues of the Dublin Evening Post (January 17, 1837 (clipping); November 23, 1837; February 25, 1837; October 2, 1838).
    -1 issue of The Morning Chronicle (June 20, 1837).
    -1 issue of The Warder (July 29, 1837).
    -1 issue of the National de 1834 (20 fevrier 1836).
    -1 issue of Courrier de la Sarthe (16 fevrier 1838).
    Boxes 8-9
    Notes and drafts for vol. II of L'Irlande
    -Extract from a speech of Mr. Wyse, July 19, 1832 in hand other than Gustave de Beaumont's.
    -Voting papers.
    -10 issues of the Dublin Evening Post (February 11, 1837; February 13, 1837; September 19, 1837; December 9, 1837; December 30, 1837; March 3, 1838; March 6, 1838; November 1, 1838; April 3, 1838; August 7, 1838)
    -2 issues of the Journal des Debats (18 octobre 1835; 5 mars 1838).
    -A bill entitled: An Act to authorize the Commissioners of his Majesty's treasury to purchase the Duties of Package, Scavage, Balliage, and Porterage belonging to the Corporation of London.]
    Boxes 10-11
    Notes and drafts for vol. II of L'lrlande.
    -"Exposition de la situation malheureux de l'Irlande", notes by _______.
    -Visiting cards of the Comte et Comtesse Louis de Beaumont and General Cass (Envoye extraordinaire et Ministre Plenipotentiaire des Etats-Unis d'Amerique pres de S.M. le Roi de France).
    -Two pages from Marie.
    -Note by Capt. Roberts.
    -Draft of letter to Salvandy, Armagh, 20 juillet 1837.
    -Note by Mr. Finlay.
    -James Armstrong, A Sermon vindicating the principles of unitarian christianity... Sunday, June 17th 1838 (With inscription).
    -George Grote, Vote by Ballot. Speech of George Grote, Esq. in the House of Commons, on the 8th of March, 1837.
    -Francis Burdett, Resolutions on Parliamentary Reform, moved by Sir Francis Burdett, in the House of Commons, on Tuesday, the 2d of June, 1818.
    -David O'Croly, An Address to the Lower Orders of the Roman Catholics of Ireland. Cork: John Bolster, 1835.
    -Discours de M. O'Connell (Extraits du National de 1834 des 24 et 25 septembre 1835).
    -Discours de M. O'Connell (Extrait du National de 1834 du 19 septembre 1835).
    -Mr. Roebuck's Democratic Speech.
    -Dr. Murray's Letter to the Rt. Hon. Lord Melbourne.... Dublin, 1835.
    -Isaac Tomkins, Thought upon the Aristocracy of England. Sixth edition. London: Henry Hooper, 1835.
    -Peter Jenkins, A Letter to Isaac Tomkins, author of Thought upon the Aristocracy. London: Henry Hooper, 1835.
    -Timothy Winterbottom, A Letter to Isaac Tomkins and Peter Jenkins on Primogeniture. Second edition. London: Williams Pickering, 1835.
    -Peter Jenkins and Isaac Tomkins, A Sketch of the Aristocracy of England, in the year 1835, by Isaac Tomkins and a Letter to that Gentleman, on the same subject, by Mr. Peter Jenkins. London: Effingham Wilson, 1835.
    -8 issues of the Dublin Evening Post (December 10, 1836; December 17, 1836; January 14, 1837 (with supplement); January 21, 1837; April 6, 1837; November 18, 1837; December 19, 1837).
    -1 issue of The Protestant Penny Magazine, Dublin (August 1835, no. XIV, vol. II).
    -1 issue of The Irish Protestant (no. XVI, vol. I, 1835).
    -2 issues of La Gazette de France (23 mai 1834; 24 mai 1834).
    -1 issue of the Journal de Paris (25 janvier 1836).
    -3 issues of the Courrier Francais (12 octobre 1835; 16 janvier 1836; 23 janvier 1836)
    -2 issues of the Journal des Debats (17 decembre 1835; 6 janvier 1836)
    -2 issues of La Paix (4 septembre 1836; 8 septembre 1836).
    Boxes 11-12
    Notes and drafts for 1862 edition of L'Irlande.
    -4 letters of Florent Richomme to Gustave de Beaumont: 18 septembre 1859; 26 septembre 1859; 3 avril 1860; 1 with no date.
    -Criticism of L'Irlande by _________.
    -1 issue of La Chronique de l'Ouest (28 mai 1862).
    -Printed letter of Desplanches to Mgr Dupanloup, eveque d'Orleans.
    - Manuscript of vol. I of L'Irlande. (Box 32)
    - Beaumont's copy of 1839 English edition, with marginalia. Manuscript of vol II of L'Irlande. (Box 33)
    - Manuscript of vol II of L'Irlande. Book catalogues and lists of books. Outline of L'Irlande. Program of 11 June 1840 session of the Academie Francaise. Prize of 6,000 Francs for L'Irlande. Lecture pour l'Academie. Notes for Vol. II. (Box 34)
    - Notes and drafts for vol. I of L'Irlande. (Box 35)
      Also includes: -Marginalia, probably by Tocqueville, in several chapters.
    - Notes and drafts for vol. I of L'Irlande. (Box 36)
    - Notes and drafts for vol. I of L'Irlande. (Box 37)
      Also includes: -Rodd to Gustave de Beaumont, London, July 3, 1837.
    - Notes and drafts for vol. I of L'Irlande. (Box 38)
    - Notes and drafts for vol. I of L'Irlande. (Box 39)
    - Notes and drafts for vol. II of L'Irlande (Box 39)
      Also includes: -Extract from a speech of Mr. Wyse, July 19, 1832 in hand other than Gustave de Beaumont's.
      -A bill entitled: An Act to authorize the Commissioners of his Majesty's treasury to purchase the Duties of Package, Scavage, Balliage, and Porterage belonging to the Corporation of London.
    - Notes and drafts for vol. II of L'Irlande (Box 40)
    - Notes and drafts for vol. II of L'lrlande. (Box 41)
      Also includes: -"Exposition de la situation malheureux de l'Irlande", notes by _______.
      -Francis Burdett, Resolutions on Parliamentary Reform, moved by Sir Francis Burdett, in the House of Commons, on Tuesday, the 2d of June, 1818. -David O'Croly, An Address to the Lower Orders of the Roman Catholics of Ireland. Cork: John Bolster, 1835.
      -8 issues of the Dublin Evening Post (December 10, 1836; December 17, 1836; January 14, 1837 (with supplement); January 21, 1837; April 6, 1837; November 18, 1837; December 19, 1837). -1 issue of The Protestant Penny Magazine, Dublin (August 1835, no. XIV, vol. II).
    - Notes and drafts for vol. II of L'lrlande. (Box 42)
    - Notes and drafts for 1862 edition of L'Irlande. (Box 42)
      Also includes: -4 letters of Florent Richomme to Gustave de Beaumont: 18 septembre 1859; 26 septembre 1859; 3 avril 1860; 1 with no date.
    - Notes and drafts for 1862 edition of L'Irlande. (Box 43)
  - Tocqueville & Beaumont 1832-1840: Miscellany, 11 (Box 44)
    a. Newspaper reviews of De la Democratie en Amerique.
    b. Manuscripts and notes.
    1. Tocqueville notes of Conversation avec Sharpe, 8 June 1835, on "Organisation politique: Parois[ses?] et Comtes." (Copy. Original sent to rejoin English travel notes in Tocqueville Tocqueville archives, 1964.)
    2. Gustave de Beaumont: Note on visit to catacombs with Mayor Richards, 21 7bre, 1834.
    3. Gustave de Beaumont: "Philosophie de l'histoire: Lois generales accidents."
    4. Gustave de Beaumont: Notes on Rivarol.
    5. Gustave de Beaumont: Notes on Sully.
    6. Gustave de Beaumont: "L'Influence des Moeurs sur les Lois"
    7. Gustave de Beaumont: "L'Homme ne pour la Societe"'
    8. Gustave de Beaumont: "Philosophie. De ce qui est vrai ou faux"
    9. Gustave de Beaumont: Latin quotes from Ulpian?
    10. Notes on Thiers's French Revolution (by both Tocqueville and Beaumont)
    11. Gustave de Beaumont Notes on Greece, 2 small folders.
    12. Tocqueville: "Visite a Kenilworth," 3 pages. (Original, from Larminat)
    13. 2 pages on English workingmen and "caisses d'epargne" (Tocqueville original, from Larminat)
    14. Pamphlet, Rev. H. Price, Reasons in Support of an Extention of the Elective Franchise..., 1836. (For this see Hume Letters, C.I.e.)
- TOCQUEVILLE & BEAUMONT, AFTER 1840; D.
  - Tocqueville - Beaumont Correspondence, 1840-1859; 1
    See also C.I.a., "Paquet 11," cahiers 1 and 2, for Gustave de Beaumont's letters to Tocqueville through 1839, copied by Bonnel.
    - a. letters of Gustave de Beaumont to Tocqueville, 1840-1848
    - b. 209 letters, Gustave de Beaumont to Tocqueville, April 1840-Aug. 1858. (Bonnel copied from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 11" cahiers 3-9. For dates and pages, see GWP itemized list clipped to cahier 3) (Box 45)
      See now:
      Correspondence d'Alexis de Tocqueville et de Gustave de Beaumont, Texte etabli, annote et preface par Andre Jardin (Tome VIII of Oeuvres Completes ), 3 vol., Gallimard, 1967.
    - c. 58 original letters, Tocqueville to Beaumont, 1840-1858. (Box 45)
      (from Larminat)
      -12 juillet, 1840, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -17 juillet, 1840, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -(28 juillet?), 1840, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -16 aout 1840, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -31 aout 1840, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -9 oct. 1843, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -8 fevr. 1848, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -1848, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -samedi, 1848, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -27 aout, 1848, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -1848, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -vendredi, 1848, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -8 mai, 1849, Bruxelles, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -18 mai, 1849, Frankfurt, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -23 mai, 1849, Bonn, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -26 mai, 1849, Bonn, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -5 dec., 1849, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -19 dec. 1849, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -9 nov. 1850, Marseille, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -24 nov., 1850, Naples, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -3 dec., 1850, Naples, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -26 dec., 1850, Sorrento, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -5 janv. 1851, Sorrento, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -29 janv. 1851, Sorrento, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -14 sept. 1851, Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -13 janv., 1852, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -7 mars, 1852, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -1 mai, 1852, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -23 mars, 1853, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -8 avril, 1853, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -3 oct. [9bre?], 1853, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -29 janv., 1854, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -16 juillet, 1854, Bonn, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -6 aout 1854, Bonn, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -20 aout, 1854, Mayence, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -1 oct. 1854, Clairvoix?, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -3 oct. 1854, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -23 oct. 1854, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -21 janv., 1855, Compiegne, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -22 oct. 1855, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -17 fevr. 1856, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -6 aout 1856, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -5 sept. 1856, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -vendredi, 1856, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -21 dec. 1856, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -15 juillet 1857, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -25 sept. 1857, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -16 oct. 1857, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -6 dec. 1857, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -2 janv. 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -10 fevr. 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -20 mars 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -18 avril 1858, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -28 mai 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -17 juin 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -27 juin 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -4 juillet, 1858, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont
      -Cannes, ce 4 mars 1859, letter to Gustave de Beaumont, pleading with him to come to them at Cannes (last letter written by Tocqueville to Beaumont). (Larminat to GWP)
  - American Relations, 1840-1861; 2
    - a. Tocqueville and Beaumont relations with Americans: letters, diaries, notes, etc. (Box 46)
      -5 Sept. 1840, Jared Sparks to Tocqueville (GWP note from H: Sparks; see C.I.d.)
      -22 Oct. 1840, Williamsburg, Va., N.B. Tucker to Francis Lieber. (Robson copy from Hunt)
      -21 Nov. 1840, Albany, J.C. Spencer to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -1 Feb. 1841, Jared Sparks to Major Poussin (GWP note from H: Sparks; see C.I.d.)
      -16 June 1841, Paris, S.G. Goodrich to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -16 aout 1841, La Grange, Gustave de Beaumont to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt; see B.IV.a.)
      -13 Oct. 1841, Jared Sparks to Prof. William Smyth (GWP note from H: Sparks; see C.I.d.)
      -2 Nov. 1841, Paris, Isaiah Townshend to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -14 aout 1842, Paris, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -29 Nov. 1842, Edward Everett to Gustave de Beaumont (Larminat)
      -6 Dec. 1842, Edward Everett to Gustave de Beaumont (Larminat)
      -15 juin 1843, Tocqueville to Niles (Original, gift of Andre Jardin)
      -9 Dec. 1843, Paris, Robert Walsh to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -27 (juin? juillet? 1844? refers to Commerce), Tocqueville to Robert Walsh. (Original with translation) (acquired by purchase)
      -15 Dec. 1843, Paris, Robert Walsh to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -22 avril 1844, Paris, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (See B.IV.a.)
      -22 mai 1844, Paris, Gustave de Beaumont to Francis Lieber (See B.IV.a.)
      -29 May 1844, Francis Lieber to wife, Paris (Robson note from Hunt)
      -31 May 1844, Paris, Gustave de Beaumont to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -11 June 1844, Brussels, Francis Lieber to wife (Robson copy from Hunt)
      -18 7bre 1844, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -13 9bre 1844, Paris, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -2 Dec. 1844, Paris, Mary Mottley and Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -8 jan. 1845-, Paris, Mary Mottley to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -18 May 1845, Paris, Tocqueville and Mary Mottley to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -1 Juillet 1845, Paris, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -6 fevrier 1846, Paris, Robert Walsh to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -13 June, 1846, Albany, Isaiah Townshend to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -22 juillet 1846, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -22 July 1846, Tocqueville, Mary Mottley to Francis Lieber (Phot from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -25 Sept. 1846, Columbia, S. C., Francis Lieber to Tocqueville (copy) (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -30 April 1848, Cambridge, Ed. Leverett to Tocqueville (Everett?) (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -10 June 1848, Albany, John C. Spencer to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -9 July 1848, Inglewood near..., W.A. Duer to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -6 March 1849, Gustave de Beaumont to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -7 mars 1849, Paris, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber (Photo from Hunt: See B.IV.a.)
      -12 May 1849, Cambridge, Edward Everett to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -23 Nov. 1849, Paris, W.W. Mann to Tocqueville (for reply see letter in Columbia University Library - Jardin) (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -27 Nov. 1849, Paris, W.W. Mann to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -12 Dec. 1849, Tocqueville to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -8 jan. 1850, Cambridge, Edward Everett to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -15 jan. 1850, Tocqueville to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -29 March 1850, Cambridge, Edward Everett to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -1 June 1850, Wash., unidentified to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -3 July 1850, Albany, John C. Spencer to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -12 Aug. 1850, Gustave de Beaumont to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -14 Oct. 1850, New York, George Bancroft to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -29 Jan. [?] 1851, Havana, Jean-Jacques Ampere to Theodore Sedgwick (GWP note from MHS: Norton; see C.I.d.)
      -24 Feb. 1851, Gustave de Beaumont to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -13 June 1851, New York, George Bancroft to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -28 June 1851, Paris, W.W. Mann to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -12 July 1851, Paris, W.W. Mann to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -30 July 1851, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton; see C.I.d.)
      -2-3 Aug. 1851, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton; see C.I.d.)
      -5 Aug. 1851, Tocqueville to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -10 Aug. 1851, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton; see C.I.d.)
      -25 and 28 Sept. 1851, Washington, T.H. Benton (GWP note from L.C.)
      -29 Nov. 1851, Fairfield, Conn., Maurice Wakerman [?] to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -2 Jan. 1852, Jean-Jacques Ampere to Theodore Sedgwick (GWP note from MHS: Norton)
      -15 March 1852, Tocqueville to Edward Everett (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -16 April 1852, Tocqueville to Edward Everett (GWP note from MHS: Everett)
      -11 May 1852, Boston, Edward Everett to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -20 May 1852, N.Y., Theodore Sedgwick to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, "Paquet 12")
      -3 July 1852, Jean-Jacques Ampere to Theodore Sedgwick (GWP note from MHS: Norton; see C.I.d.)